Guide to the Kensinger Jones Papers, 1934-2001 and undated RL.00648
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kensinger Jones papers
1934-2002 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jones, Kensinger, 1919-
RL.00648
37 Linear Feet
Advertising executive, 1950s-1980s. The collection documents Jones's primary career as an executive for several major advertising agencies, including Leo Burnett Company, Campbell-Ewald Company, D.P. Brother and Company, Wilding Advertising, and William R.Biggs/Gilmore Associates; and his second career as a professor of advertising at Michigan State University. Materials consist primarily of correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, scripts, and audiovisual (including videocassettes) materials that document the development of print, radio, and television advertising campaigns for a wide variety of clients. The history and management of advertising companies in Chicago and Detroit, in Australia, and in Singapore is also represented. Major clients and campaigns documented include Chevrolet, the Florida Citrus Commission, General Motors Corporation, and Oldsmobile.
22,500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
The "Course Materials" subseries of the Michigan State Series is closed to researchers pending review by the collector. Original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers until use copies can be produced.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Kensinger Jones Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1999-2001.
Biographical Note
1919, Oct. 18 Born in St. Louis, Mo., to Walter C. and Anna (Kensinger) Jones
1937 Graduated from Roosevelt High School
1938-1939 Nadine College of Advertising, St. Louis
1939-1940 Washington University
1941-1944 138th Infantry: Alaska; 337th CTD Pennsylvania
1944, Oct. 7 Married Alice May Guseman, Pa. Children: Jeffrey Kensinger, b.1948; Janice Anne, b. 1950
1944-1952 Freelance writer, St. Louis, for Radio Stations KMOX and KSD, Premier Radio Enterprises, Gardner Advertising Agency, and local government and non-profit agencies
1952-1957, Aug. Leo Burnett Company, Chicago: Copywriter, Television and Radio Department; and TV Group Head (1955)
1957, Aug.-1967 Campbell-Ewald Company, Detroit: Creative Director for TV and Radio, Vice President, 1957-1960; Senior Vice President and Creative Director, 1960-1966; Executive Vice President and Creative Director, 1966-1967
1959 Grand Prix, Cannes International Film Festival, for "An American in Paris"
1961 Grand Prix, Cannes International Film Festival, for "The Magic Ride"
1968-1970 D.P. Brother Company, Detroit: Senior Vice President and Executive Creative Director
1971-1973, Mar. Leo Burnett Company, Chicago: Senior Vice President and Executive Creative Director
1973, Mar.-1974, Apr. Leo Burnett Pty. Ltd., Sydney, Australia: Regional Creative Director
1974, Apr.-Dec. Leo Burnett Pte. Ltd, Singapore, Malaysia: Regional Creative Director
1974, Dec. 31 Retired from Leo Burnett Company
1975-1976 Consultant to Leo Burnett Company, Chicago and Leo Burnett Pte., Ltd, Singapore, Malaysia
1975- Writer, farmer, Barry County, Mich.
1979 Wilding Advertising, Southfield, Mich.: Creative consultant
1981-1983 William R. Biggs/Gilmore, Kalamazoo, Mich.: Creative Supervisor
1982-1995 Lecturer, Department of Advertising, Michigan State University
1988 Visiting Lecturer, People's Republic of China, U.S. Exchange Program in Advertising
1990 Visiting Lecturer, Taipei, Taiwan and Jakarta, Indonesia
1992 Visiting Lecturer, Dalhousie University, Nova Scotia
1996 Professor Emeritus, Michigan State University
Other awards include the American Film Festival, Best of Automotive Award, 1961; Film Festival Hall of Fame for two commercials, 1965; and the American Freedoms Award, 1985
Collection Overview
The Kensinger Jones Papers, 1934-2001, document Jones's primary career as an executive for several major advertising agencies, including Leo Burnett Company, Campbell-Ewald Company, D.P. Brother and Company, Wilding Advertising, and William R.Biggs/Gilmore Associates; and his second career as a professor of advertising at Michigan State University. Materials consist primarily of correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, scripts, and audiovisual materials that document the development of print, radio, and television advertising campaigns for a wide variety of clients. The history and management of advertising companies in Chicago and Detroit in the United States, in Australia, and in Singapore is also represented. Major clients documented include Chevrolet, the Florida Citrus Commission, General Motors Corporation, and Oldsmobile.
The Advertising Agencies Series, the largest, includes memoranda and correspondence related to the executive management of each agency and Jones's role in organizing and directing the creative activities of the agency or advertising team. Materials from Jones's work at the Leo Burnett Company consist primarily of office memoranda and weekly progress reports for radio and television commercials for clients such as: Mars, Incorporated; Kellogg Company; and the Green Giant Company. In Southeast Asia, Jones served as Regional Creative Director for Leo Burnett offices in Sydney, Singapore, Kuala Lumpur, Hong Kong and Bangkok. Materials include correspondence, speeches for creative seminars, and scripts for two films for the Singapore Tourist Promotion Board. Jones worked mainly with clients in the automotive industry, specifically Chevrolet at the Campbell-Ewald Company and Oldsmobile at D.P. Brother Company (as well as at Leo Burnett). Materials about General Motors relate to the potential of television specials for corporate advertising to promote the GM "Mark of Excellence" and the corporation's responsiveness to environmental and safety issues in the late sixties and seventies. Closely related to the Advertising Agencies Series, the Correspondence and Memoranda Series consists of carbons of outgoing correspondence from Jones, filed in chronological order with some memoranda.
Nearly a third of the collection pertains to Jones's tenure from 1982-1995 as Lecturer in the Department of Advertising, the School of Communication Arts at Michigan State University. The Michigan State University (MSU) Series includes correspondence with colleagues and students, materials from academic conferences and MSU's Visiting Advertising Professional program, as well as copies of Impact, the alumni newsletter for the Advertising Department. Of particular note are materials related to China and Taiwan in 1988 and 1990. The Course Materials Subseries details his advanced courses in creative advertising. In order to create a realistic, professional experience for the students, Jones assigned group projects that required students to create advertising campaigns or marketing strategies for national or state clients, local businesses, and university departments, including Archway Cookies, Oldsmobile, McDonalds, American Tourister, the Muskegon County Museum, and several MSU facilities and departments. The projects were presented to the class and evaluated not only by the client and Professor Jones, but also by the other students.
Throughout his life, Jones considered himself primarily to be a writer, and the Writings and Speeches Series reflects Jones's lifelong writing efforts. The series includes a wide variety of professional, personal, and unpublished writing: advertising presentations, speeches, articles, advertising seminars, scripts for radio programs and plays, poetry, an unpublished novel, and an autobiography. The Speeches Subseries and Published Articles Subseries document his creativity in advertising and his contributions to the industry as well as to local schools and organizations. Material in the Personal Series demonstrates his activities with professional and civic organizations; in addition this series contains personal correspondence and materials about the life and career of Leo Burnett.
Much of Jones's creative work in advertising was produced for the broadcast media, especially the early days of television advertising in the 1950s and 1960s. The Audiovisual Materials Series includes film and sound materials that document television advertising and Jones's creative contributions to the professional education of his advertising colleagues. Because several of his most successful films about advertising or creativity originated as speeches with slides, these materials are particularly rich in conjunction with related materials in the Writings and Speeches Series.
Television advertising -- United States -- History; Automobiles -- Marketing; Advertising -- Automobiles; Advertising, Public service -- United States; Advertising agencies; Television advertising -- Video recordings; Radio advertising; Brand name products; Advertising agencies -- Australia; Scripts (documents); Advertising agencies -- Asia; Advertising -- Study and teaching -- United States; Advertising -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- History -- 20th century; Advertising agencies -- Michigan -- Detroit; Advertising agencies -- Illinois -- Chicago; Advertising agencies -- Employees; Advertising executives; Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising agencies -- Singapore; Campbell-Ewald Company; Burnett, Leo, 1891-; Florida Citrus Commission; D.P. Brother and Company; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; General Motors Corporation; Jones, Kensinger, 1919-; Wilding Advertising; William R. Biggs/Gilmore Associates; Leo Burnett Company; Michigan State University
- Advertising Agencies, 1952-1983 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged in subseries for each agency where Jones worked; subseries appear chronologically by the date that Jones first worked at each agency. This series consists primarily of office memoranda, correspondence, scripts for advertising presentations to clients, scripts for television or radio commercials, newspaper and magazine articles, and a few photographs. An Information Folder found in the inventory drawer at the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library contains additional biographical data and a description of Jones's positions with each agency. See individual subseries for more specific arrangement notes.
  - Leo Burnett Company, Chicago, 1952-1957; 1971-1973; 1973-1976, and undated
    Arranged by three chronological time periods, when Jones held different positions with the agency in Chicago and South East Asia. Within each time period, the folders are arranged alphabetically.
    - 1952-1957 (Box 1)
      - Broadcast Continuities, various clients, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
      - Color TV memoranda, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
      - Finally Somebody Has to Get Out an Ad, Burnett speech, 1955 Oct. 13 (Box 1)
      - Job Application and Work Samples, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
      - Leo Burnett Company. Archive materials, 1955-1956, 1968, 1989, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Lest We Forget-A Television History ... 1931-1952. Script (not produced) re the Democratic Party, 1952 (Box 1)
      - Memoranda, miscellaneous, 1955-1957 (Box 1)
      - Office Memoranda from Leo Burnett or R.N. Heath, 1953-1957, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Pick Yourself a Problem, campaign for the American Heritage Foundation. Ad proofs (16x22), 1968 (Box 1)
      - Scripts, storyboards, and memos, re clients: Kellogg, Commonwealth Edison, Procter and Gamble, and Mars, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
      - A Study of Attitudes Toward Chrysler Corporation and its Cars, 1962 July (Box 2)
      - Weekly reports, Group 2, 1954-1955 (Box 2)
    - 1971-1973
      - "Articles worth saving--client and competitive," including memos and notes, 1965-1972 (Box 2)
      - Chicago Better Business Bureau, 1971-1973 and undated (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1970-1973 (Box 2)
      - [Creative Department] Memos: :30s vs :60s and 11 golden rules for :30's (Box 2)
      - Creative Quality Control at Burnett: An In-Depth Appraisal, [ca. 1969] (Box 2)
      - D.P. Brother and Company, Detroit [renamed Leo Burnett Company of Michigan in 1971]. Operating Procedures, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      - Drug Abuse: Conference on Communication and Drug Abuse by the National Association for the Prevention of Addiction to Narcotics and J. Walter Thompson Company, 1972 Nov.-Dec. (Box 2)
      - Federal Trade Commission, 1971-1973 (Box 3)
      - Florida Citrus Commission, 1971, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - General Motors Corporation, 1971-1972, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Legal Substantiation, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - Management memoranda, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
      - New Business: United States Travel Service, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Oldsmobile-Creative Group F-1, 1971-1972 (Box 4)
      - Oldsmobile-1972 Model Year
        - Dealer Point of Sale material, 1970-1972 (Box 4)
        - Ninety Eight: Quite a Substantial Car, 1971 (Box 4)
        - Planning, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
        - Pollution, 1969-1972 (Box 4)
        - Presentations, 1971 (Box 4)
        - Safety and ecology, 1971 (Box 4)
        - Statements of Advertising Objectives and 1972 Strategies, 1970-1971 (Box 4)
      - Oldsmobile-1973 Model Year (Box 5)
        - Exhibits and Scripts, 1972, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Forecast re the 1980 marketplace for automotive advertising, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
        - Memoranda, scripts, and presentations to GM, 1972 (Box 5)
        - Omega (X-car), correspondence and memos about development and marketing, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
        - Planning: office memoranda and correspondence, 1972 (Box 5)
        - Press Releases and Photographs, 1972-1973, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Statements of Advertising Objectives and 1973 Strategies, 1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Timetable/meetings, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Pillsbury, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Producers and suppliers for media advertising correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
      - Product Group Assignments, October 16, 1972 (Box 6)
      - Public Service Communications Council of Chicago (PSCCC)
        - Activities in other Cities, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
        - Advertising Campaigns, 1971-1973 (Box 6)
        - Correspondence and proposals for setting up the PSCCC, 1971 (Box 7)
        - Correspondence and memos on PSCCC activities on venereal disease and pedestrian safety, 1972 (Box 7)
        - Information folder, 1971-1972 (Box 7)
        - Operations Committee, Agendas and Meeting Reports, 1971-1973, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Resignation from Leo Burnett Company, USA; memoranda and correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 7)
      - Truth in Advertising: correspondence on symposium at the University of Toronto, 1972 Nov.-Dec. (Box 7)
      - Williams, Lowell: correspondence requesting position at Leo Burnett, Feb. 7 1973, 1963-1964, 1973 (Box 7)
      - Year-end report to Burnett People and related materials, 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 8)
      - The Advertisers Association, Singapore. Speeches, 1974, 1976, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Advertising Code of Ethics, 1973 and undated (Box 8)
      - ASEAN [Association of South East Asian Nations] Presentation Report, 1976, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Australian Dairy Board, 1973 (Box 8)
      - Bangkok regional office, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
      - Brisbane regional office, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
      - Business and Health Insurance, 1974 (Box 8)
      - Business Correspondence: re employment in Southeast Asia, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
      - Business Correspondence: re income tax return, Republic of Singapore, and personal financial assets, 1977 (Box 8)
      - Business expenses and travel schedules to regional offices, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
      - [Consultant to Leo Burnett, (South East Asia)] 1975-1976, folders 1-2 of 4 (Box 8)
      - [Consultant to Leo Burnett, (South East Asia)] 1975-1976, folders 3-4 of 4 (Box 9)
      - Creative Seminars, Kuala Lumpur, speeches: The Minstrel Principle and Some Advertising that Works, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
      - Creative Seminar, Singapore. Leo Burnett's Creative Beliefs, March 26-27, 1975 (Box 9)
      - [Credentials Booklet]-"Leo Burnett Pty. Limited," May, 1972 (Box 9)
      - [Credentials Booklet]-"Leo Burnett, International-Bangkok," 1973? (Box 9)
      - General Motors Corporation (South East Asia), 1973-1974 (Box 9)
      - Guild Marketing Company Pty. Limited - "A Commentary.. ." April 6, 1973 (Box 9)
      - Hardboards Australia Ltd, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
      - Hong Kong regional office, 1973 (Box 9)
      - Jardine, Matheson, and Co. Ltd., 1974 (Box 9)
      - Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia) regional office, 1973, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Levi, scripts for commercials, 1973 (Box 9)
      - Leo Burnett Company correspondence, 1973-1977, Folder 1 of 5 (Box 9)
      - Leo Burnett Company correspondence, 1973-1977, Folders 2-5 of 5 (Box 10)
      - Leo Burnett Company newsletters: Leo Burnett World News, and News From Around the World 1971-1977 (Box 10)
      - Leo Burnett Company newsletters: Leo Burnett USA News, 1972-1973 (Box 10)
      - London office. Hixon, Carl, correspondence and exhibits, 1973 (Box 10)
      - London office. Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 10)
      - London office. List of commercials for Nestle presentation, May 6, 1976 (Box 10)
      - MAS (Malaysia Air System) 1977-1978 Campaign, Nov, 1976 (Box 10)
      - New Business: General New Business Presentation re the four I's of advertising, 1974? (Box 10)
      - Personal correspondence, 1973-1974, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Personnel, correspondence and memoranda, 1973-1975 (Box 11)
      - Publications on South East Asia, 1975-1977 (Box 11)
      - Qantas Airways Limited. Brief and analysis, [ca. 1970s] (Box 11)
      - Qantas Airways Limited. Advertising Presentation, Australian Region, March 26, 1973 (Box 11)
      - Regional Creative Director - Correspondence, 1973-1975, 5 folders (Box 11)
      - Rice Marketing Board for the State of New South Wales. Media plan and budget, Jul-Aug, 1973 (Box 12)
      - Rothmans International. Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia) regional office, 1973 (Box 12)
      - Singapore Convention Bureau, Creative and Media Recommendations, fiscal 1975-76, 1974 (Box 12)
      - Singapore regional office: Correspondence and copies of Singapore Travel News, 1973-1974 (Box 12)
      - Singapore regional office: Correspondence and materials related to advertising in Singapore and S.E Asia, 1974-1975 (Box 12)
      - Singapore regional office: Correspondence with J. Flynn of Tokyo regional office, re conflicts with the Singapore Tourist Promotion Board account and with the marketing films, April-May, 1975 (Box 12)
      - Singapore Tourist Promotion Board
        - Consultant trip, 1976 Sept.-Nov. (Box 12)
        - Creative and Media Recommendations... 1974 Feb., 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Film Projects, 1973-1975
          - Background materials and scripts for Singapore: A Child of my Own, 1974 Jun. 24 and Singapore Speaks, undated, 1973-1975 (Box 12)
          - Correspondence, re revisions, production, and comments; (includes script for Singapore-Child of My Own), 1974-1975 (Box 13)
          - Correspondence and notes for two film projects: Where the World Comes Together and A Child of My Own, 1974-1975 (Box 13)
          - Where the World Comes Together: Singapore, Convention City. Production notes and scripts, 1974-1975 (Box 13)
        - Marketing, Sales, Advertising for Fiscal 1976-77, 1975 Oct. 21 (Box 13)
        - Presentation, re marketing and advertising, 1975 (aboard boat, Rasa Sayang) (Box 13)
        - Publications, 1971-1975, 2 folders
          - -- Travel Agent - Manual, 1975: Welcome to Singapore handbook 1975; Singapore Weekly Guide, March 1975, 1974-1975 (Box 13)
          - -- Convention City, Singapore: Where the World Comes Together 1974 and earlier edition Singapore: Convention Center of the East 1971, 1971, 1974 (Box 13)
        - South Pacific Advertising, Fiscal 1977-1978, 1976 Oct. (Box 14)
      - Sydney office. Creative Procedures, 1973-1974, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Sydney office. General, 1973-1974 (including schedule for visit by P. Schaff, President Leo Burnett Company, Chicago, March, 1974) (Box 14)
      - Tasmania, undated (Box 14)
      - Waltons Limited, 1973-1974 (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous: "The Corporate Image in the New Age and Mergers: A Time for Re-appraisal," study by Leo Burnett and Company, speech, and related correspondence, 1967, 1971, and undated (Box 14)
  - Campbell-Ewald Company, Detroit, 1957-1967 and undated
    Arranged alphabetically by major subject categories that correspond to Jones's work as Creative Director and Executive Vice-President. Major accounts include Chevrolet, General Motors, Florida Citrus Commission, and other new business prospects. Many of the files pertain to the operation and reorganization of the Creative Department as well as the management of the agency, when Jones served on the Executive Committee. Several Chevrolet film commercials won awards at notable advertising competitions. The papers also reflect Jones's focus on professional development -- coordinating seminars within the agency, writing articles, and presenting workshops with state, regional, and national advertising organizations. One effort resulted in the Creativity film, later renamed the Horse and the Fiddle. Another, Whatever Happened to Mrs. Momiyama, related the role of advertising in a free economy and the resurgence of the Japanese economy after WWII. Both a filmstrip and a film version were distributed by the American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA) to high schools and colleges. See also the Audiovisual Materials Series.
    - AAAA (Box 15)
      - The Adman (Thought Leader Version), 1962 (Box 15)
      - Four brochures (incl. one by Leo Burnett), 1961-1963 (Box 15)
      - Whatever Happened to Mrs. Momiyama: correspondence and materials on converting film into an educational filmstrip, 1963-1966 (Box 15)
    - Articles
      - Ad Making and Communication, 1960-1966 and undated, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Advertising Industry, 1961-1967, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 15)
      - Advertising Industry, 1961-1967, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 16)
      - Automobile and Automobile Industry, 1962 (Box 16)
      - Management, 1961-1966 and undated (Box 16)
      - Radio and Television, 1961-1966 (Box 16)
      - [Untitled] by Leo Rosten, The University of Chicago Magazine [1962] (Box 16)
    - Awards
      - American TV Commercials Festival and Forum; correspondence; newsletters, 1960 (Box 16)
      - Cannes Film Festival, 1959 (Box 16)
    - Clients
      - Boeing: Presentation, 1964 Jan. 24 (Box 16)
      - Chevrolet
        - Ad Committee Review, 1962 (Box 16)
        - 1961 model year - Invisible Car Commercial, Magic Ride; correspondence; script, 1959-1960 (Box 16)
        - 1963-66 model years: Youth Market, memos; speeches; report of 1962 Male College Student Survey, 1963-1964 (Box 16)
        - 1967 model year: An Evaluation of Four Major Advertising Media as Used by the GM Automotive Divisions and Their Competition [undated] (Box 17)
        - 1967 model year: Market-by Market Campaign - Research, 1966-1967 (Box 17)
        - 1968 model year - "Talk to Creative Staff, February 10, 1967;" re new General Sales Manager for Chevrolet (Box 17)
        - Photographs, ca. 1960 (Box 17)
      - Delco Project 66 Presentation (Box 17)
      - Detroit Edison Presentation, 1964 May 12 (Box 17)
      - Firestone presentations, 1963, 1967, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Florida Citrus Commission
        - Presentation, 1961 Oct. 11 (Box 17)
        - Presentation, 1962 Aug. 2 (Box 17)